<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short account of the expiring Parl--m-nt.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1713</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.2[239]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99894789</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99894789</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A1:1[242])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short account of the expiring Parl--m-nt.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>3 leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Newcomb in Wine-Office-Court, Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1713.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Some mighty genius how my breast inspire".</note>
                  <note>Drop head title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Printed on one side of the leaf only, the last on the verso.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parliamentary practice --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:181561:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 143 -->
            <head>A ſhort ACCOUNT OF THE Expiring Parl—m—nt.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SOme mighty Genius now my Breaſt inſpire</l>
               <l>With ſomething more than a Seraph<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck Fire;</l>
               <l>Bold ſhining Thoughts into my Soul infuſe</l>
               <l>Above the reach of ev'ry vulgar Muſe.</l>
               <l>They, who like me, Heroic Souls would praiſe,</l>
               <l>Should riſe above the pitch of common Lays:</l>
               <l>'The nobleſt Subjects nobleſt Thoughts require,</l>
               <l>My Subject's worthy the Angelick Quire,</l>
               <l>Immortal Cherubs ſhould their Praiſes ſing,</l>
               <l>And pluck their Quills forth from an Angel's Wing.</l>
               <l>How large, how ſpacious is the glorious Scene,</l>
               <l>No leſs than <hi>Britain</hi>'s Happineſs the Theme.</l>
               <l>Her Reſcue too from thoſe deſigning <hi>Sons</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who their fond <hi>Mother</hi> had almoſt undone;</l>
               <l>Sought out each treacherous undermining way</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Country's Freedom</hi> baſely to betray.</l>
               <l>What then is to that <hi>Glorious SENATE</hi> due</l>
               <l>That ſav'd their <hi>Country</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> too?</l>
               <l>What Monuments, what Altars can we raiſe</l>
               <l>To celebrate ſuch God-like Hero's praiſe?</l>
               <l>Their own immortal Acts ſufficient are</l>
               <l>Their Fame to future Ages to declare:</l>
               <l>But yet 'tis juſt a grateful Sence to ſhow</l>
               <l>For all the Toll for us they undergo.</l>
               <l>Long had the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Realm, by <hi>Faction</hi> rui'd,</l>
               <l>Been cheated, bubbled, ridicul'd and fool'd:</l>
               <l>The Reverence ſhould their <hi>Sovereign</hi> been ſhown.</l>
               <l>On <hi>Party Factions</hi> was beſtow'd alone;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:181561:2"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 144 -->
To that alone the <hi>S—te</hi> Homage paid,</l>
               <l>And at the gilded Shrine their <hi>Queen</hi> enſlav'd,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Pelf</hi> their Country and their God they ſold,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Loyalty</hi> a Tribute gave to Gold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Britain</hi>'s Genius (tho' almoſt too late)</l>
               <l>Aſpiring roſe, by the Decrees of Fate,</l>
               <l>Her much lov'd, tho' her ſinking Realm to ſave,</l>
               <l>She could not ſee <hi>Britannia</hi> be a Slave.</l>
               <l>Long had ſhe found a ſubtle Factious Race</l>
               <l>The noble Places they enjoy'd diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At length the <hi>People</hi> ſh' with juſt Rage inſpir'd,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry Breaſt with dire Reſentment fir'd:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Subjects</hi> mourn'd their long miſguided Choice,</l>
               <l>And gave at length for <hi>Loyaliſts</hi> their Voice.</l>
               <l>Nor ſooner had the worthy <hi>Patriots</hi> ſate</l>
               <l>But they reviv'd the poor declining <hi>State;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reſtor'd their antient <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Juſtly aſſerting injur'd <hi>England</hi>'s Cauſe:</l>
               <l>Examin'd why, after great Battels won,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Conqueror</hi> was always moſt undone?</l>
               <l>Where the vaſt Sums of Treaſure were convey'd</l>
               <l>Were by the injur'd People yearly paid?</l>
               <l>Why the poor <hi>Soldiers</hi> were ſo ſhortly fed</l>
               <l>When <hi>England</hi> paid ſo many Pounds for Bread?</l>
               <l>So far they ſearch'd into the dangerous Wound</l>
               <l>Ev'n the firſt Cauſes of the Sore they found,</l>
               <l>And tho' no mighty Man a Victim fell</l>
               <l>To the juſt Stroak of the revenging Steel,</l>
               <l>'Twas Mercy, not Deſert, the Villains ſav'd</l>
               <l>That had their Native Realm ſo far enſlav'd:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Royal Goodneſs</hi> only ſtept between,</l>
               <l>And they were freed by their much-injur'd QUEEN.</l>
               <l>This Point with eaſe the <hi>Loyal SENATE</hi> gains,</l>
               <l>But a far greater Work there yet remains,</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Freedom</hi> and her <hi>Credit</hi> to Reſtore,</l>
               <l>And ſatisfie thoſe <hi>Debts</hi> ſhe ow'd before;</l>
               <l>For which to diſtant Realms a Fleet is ſent</l>
               <l>To perfect the illuſtrious Intent:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:181561:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 145 -->
O'er the wide ſpacious Deep, ſecure they ride</l>
               <l>Whilſt their ſharp Keels the ſwelling Waves divide;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Southern</hi> World to <hi>ANNE</hi> does tribute pay,</l>
               <l>And at her Feet the richeſt Product lay,</l>
               <l>Which wi'l her Loſſes and her Debts defray.</l>
               <l>In vain do's <hi>Faction</hi> raiſe her ſnaky Head</l>
               <l>And curſe the approaching Happineſs ſhe dreads;</l>
               <l>In vain at their wiſe Councils ſhe repines</l>
               <l>She cannot fruſtrate their brave Deſigns;</l>
               <l>She grins to think the wiſh'd-for Timé draws near</l>
               <l>Will free her from the Foes ſhe moſt does fear:</l>
               <l>She thinks her Empire to re-obtain,</l>
               <l>And ſway again with a Tyrannick Rein.</l>
               <l>But Heav'n, who has ſo oft its Goodneſs ſhown,</l>
               <l>Her Great <hi>Vicogerent</hi> will not ceaſe to own;</l>
               <l>And God, who rul'd ſo late the Peoples Voice,</l>
               <l>Will guide them to Confirm the worthy Choice.</l>
               <l>For as for ſecret Cauſes Heav'n ordains</l>
               <l>The <hi>Phoenix</hi> ſhould expire in ſpicey Flames,</l>
               <l>But from the Aſhes does the Bird reſtore</l>
               <l>With far more Vigour than ſhe had before.</l>
               <l>Entomb'd ſhe lies but for a moment's ſpace,</l>
               <l>Her Funeral Pile becomes a pregnant Place:</l>
               <l>The wond'rous Species do's ſtill revive,</l>
               <l>And often tho' he dies, do's always live.</l>
               <l>Thus tho' by Cuſtom this Great <hi>SENATE</hi> dies,</l>
               <l>In ſpite of <hi>Faction</hi> 'twill again ariſe.</l>
               <l>Brave and Reſolv'd it will again appear,</l>
               <l>Nor a <hi>declining Miniſtry</hi> will fear:</l>
               <l>True to their <hi>Country's Intereſt</hi> they'l move,</l>
               <l>And ſhow at once their Duty and their Love;</l>
               <l>VVith greater Vigour they'l again revive,</l>
               <l>And in the Books of Fame for ever live;</l>
               <l>And greater Bleſſings may they ſtill poſſéſs,</l>
               <l>Their év'ry Act <hi>meet with</hi> deſir'd <hi>Succeſs.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And if <hi>Cabals</hi> or <hi>Plots</hi> their <hi>Peace</hi> annoy,</l>
               <l>Short may their <hi>Trouble,</hi> laſting be their <hi>Joy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London: <hi>Printed by</hi> R. Newcomb <hi>in</hi> Wine-Office-Court, Fleet-ſtreet, <hi>1713.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
